My story is a little bit about war.
تتحدث قصتي قليلا عن الحرب.
It's about disillusionment.
تتحدث عن خيبة الأمل.
It's about death.
عن الموت.
And it's about rediscovering
عن إعادة اكتشاف
idealism
المثالية
in all of that wreckage.
في كل ماهو محطم.
And perhaps also, there's a lesson
وربما أيضا، في ذلك درس
about how to deal with
في كيفية التعامل مع
our screwed-up, fragmenting
عالم القرن الـ 21 المتصف بالتشرذم و الحماقات
and dangerous world of the 21st century.
و الخطورة.
I don't believe in straightforward narratives.
لا أؤمن بالقصص السردية .
I don't believe in a life or history
ولا بقصة
written as decision "A" led to consequence "B"
مكتوبة حيث القرار "أ" أدى إلى النتيجة "ب"
led to consequence "C" --
التي أدت إلى النتيجة "ج"--
these neat narratives that we're presented with,
هذه الطرق السردية الأنيقة التي نقدم بها أنفسنا،
and that perhaps we encourage in each other.
و التي قد نشجع بعضنا على فعلها.
I believe in randomness,
أؤمن بالعشوائية،
and one of the reasons I believe that
ومن الأسباب التي جعلتني أفكر هكذا
is because me becoming a diplomat was random.
أنني أصبحت دبلوماسيا بمحض الصدفة.
I'm colorblind.
فأنا مصاب بعمى الألوان.
I was born unable to see most colors.
ولدت مع عدم القدرة على رؤية الألوان
This is why I wear gray and black most of the time,
لذلك فأنا أرتدي اللونين الرمادي و الأسود معظم الوقت،
and I have to take my wife with me
وعليَّ اصطحاب زوجتي معي
to chose clothes.
لاختيار الملابس.
And I'd always wanted to be a fighter pilot when I was a boy.
كنت دائما أحلم أن أكون طيارا محاربا عندما كنت صغيرا.
I loved watching planes barrel over
كنت أحب مشاهدة الطائرات المحلقة بسرعة فوق
our holiday home in the countryside.
بيتنا الصيفي في الريف.
And it was my boyhood dream to be a fighter pilot.
فكان حلم طفولتي أن أكون طيارا مقاتلا.
And I did the tests in the Royal Air Force to become a pilot,
و قد أجريت امتحانات القوات الجوية الملكية لأصبح طيارا،
and sure enough, I failed.
وبكل تأكيد ، فقد فشلت.
I couldn't see all the blinking different lights,
فلم يكن بمقدوري رؤية الأضواء الوامضة المختلفة،
and I can't distinguish color.
ولا تمييز الألوان.
So I had to choose another career,
لذا كان علي أن أختار مسارا مهنيا آخرا،
and this was in fact relatively easy for me,
وهذا الأمر في الواقع كان سهلا نسبيا بالنسبة لي،
because I had an abiding passion all the way through my childhood,
فلقد كان عندي شغف كبير منذ طفولتي،
which was international relations.
بالعلاقات الدولية.
As a child,
عندما كنت طفلا،
I read the newspaper thoroughly.
كنت أقرأ الجريدة كاملة.
I was fascinated by the Cold War,
كنت منبهرا بالحرب الباردة،
by the INF negotiations
بالمفاوضات
over intermediate-range nuclear missiles,
حول الصواريخ النووية متوسطة المدى،
the proxy war between the Soviet Union and the U.S.
الحرب التفاوضية بين الاتحاد السوڤياتي و الولايات المتحدة.
in Angola or Afghanistan.
في أنغولا و أفعانستان.
These things really interested me.
هذه الأشياء كانت مثار اهتمامي حقيقةً.
And so I decided quite at an early age
لذا قررتُ و في سن مبكر نسبيا
I wanted to be a diplomat.
أن أصبح دبلوماسيا.
And I, one day, I announced this to my parents --
و في أحد الأيام أعلنت هذا لوالديَّ--
and my father denies this story to this day --
ولا زال والدي ينكر هذه القصة إلى اليوم--
I said, "Daddy, I want to be a diplomat."
قلت له : "أبي ،أريد أن أصبح دبلوماسيا"
And he turned to me, and he said,
فالتفت إليَّ، ثم قال،
"Carne, you have to be very clever to be a diplomat."
"عليك أن تكون ذكي جدا إن أردت أن تصبح دبلوماسيا".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And my ambition was sealed.
ومنذ ذلك الحين، تبخر طموحي.
In 1989,
في سنة 1989،
I entered the British Foreign Service.
انخرطتُ في الخدمة الخارجية البريطانية.
That year, 5,000 people applied to become a diplomat,
في ذلك العام 5000 شخص تقدم لتلك الوظيفة
and 20 of us succeeded.
لكن 20 فقط منا تم قبولهم.
And as those numbers suggest,
وكما أشارت الأرقام السابقة،
I was inducted into an elite
فقد ولجتُ عالم النخبة
and fascinating and exhilarating world.
عالمٌ بهيجٌ ومدهش.
Being a diplomat, then and now,
أعتبر كوني دبلوماسيا ، عندئذٍ كما الآن،
is an incredible job, and I loved every minute of it --
مهنة مدهشة ، إذ أنني أستمتع بكل دقيقة فيها.
I enjoyed the status of it.
كنت أستمتع بمقامها.
I bought myself a nice suit and wore leather-soled shoes
اشتريت لنفسي طقما وحذاء مصنوعا من الجلد
and reveled in
ومن ثم انخرطت
this amazing access I had to world events.
في الاحداث العالمية المميزة
I traveled to the Gaza Strip.
سافرتُ إلى قطاع غزة.
I headed the Middle East Peace Process section
فقد كنت أترأس قسم السلام في الشرق الأوسط
in the British Foreign Ministry.
في وزارة الخارجية البريطانية.
I became a speechwriter
أصبحت محرر خطابات
for the British Foreign Secretary.
لوزير الخارجية البريطاني.
I met Yasser Arafat.
التقيتُ بياسر عرفات.
I negotiated
تفاوضت
with Saddam's diplomats at the U.N.
مع دبلوماسيي صدام حسين في الأمم المتحدة.
Later, I traveled to Kabul
لاحقا، سافرتُ إلى كابل
and served in Afghanistan after the fall of the Taliban.
و عملتُ في أفغانستان بعد سقوط طالبان.
And I would travel
كنت لأسافر
in a C-130 transport
في طائرة نقل 130-C العسكرية
and go and visit warlords
وأذهب للقاء زعماء الحرب
in mountain hideaways
في الجبال الوعرة
and negotiate with them
والتفاوض معهم
about how we were going to eradicate Al Qaeda from Afghanistan,
حول كيفية عملنا للتخلص من القاعدة من أفغانستان،
surrounded by my Special Forces escort,
كنت أذهب محاطا بقوة مرافقة خاصة،
who, themselves, had to have an escort of a platoon of Royal Marines,
محاطون هم بدورهم بقوة مرافقة من البحرية الملكية،
because it was so dangerous.
لأن الوضع كان خطيرا جدا.
And that was exciting -- that was fun.
لكنه كان شيقا و ممتعا أيضا.
It was really interesting.
كان مثيرا للاهتمام فعلا.
And it's a great cadre of people,
كان إطار العمل رائعا جدا.
incredibly close-knit community of people.
كنا مجموعة عمل مترابطة بشكل كبير.
And the pinnacle of my career, as it turned out,
كانت نقطة التحول في مساري المهني،
was when I was posted to New York.
عندما أُرسلتُ إلى نيويورك.
I'd already served in Germany, Norway,
عملتُ أيضا في ألمانيا ، النرويج،
various other places,
في أماكن أخرى متنوعة،
but I was posted to New York
لكنني أُرسلتُ إلى نيويورك
to serve on the U.N. Security Council for the British delegation.
للعمل في البعثة البريطانية في مجلس الأمن الدولي.
And my responsibility was the Middle East,
كنت مسؤولا عن الشرق الأوسط.
which was my specialty.
الذي كان من اختصاصي.
And there, I dealt with things
وهناك اهتممتُ بعدة مواضيع
like the Middle East peace process,
مثل مسلسل السلام في الشرق الأوسط،
the Lockerbie issue --
قضية لوكربي--
we can talk about that later, if you wish --
يمكننا التحدث حول هذا لاحقا ، إن أردتم --
but above all, my responsibility was Iraq
لكن فوق كل هذا، كان العراق مسؤوليتي الأولى
and its weapons of mass destruction
وأسلحة الدمار الشامل
and the sanctions we placed on Iraq
والعقوبات التي فرضناها على العراق
to oblige it to disarm itself of these weapons.
لإجباره على التخلي عن هذه الأسلحة.
I was the chief British negotiator
كنت كبير المفاوضين البريطانيين
on the subject,
عن هذا الملف،
and I was steeped in the issue.
وكنت منغمسا جدا في هذه القضايا.
And anyway,
على أي حال،
my tour -- it was kind of a very exciting time.
جولتي-- كانت عبارة عن وقت مثير جدا.
I mean it was very dramatic diplomacy.
أعني كانت ديبلوماسية مؤثرة جدا.
We went through several wars
مرت علينا حروب عديدة
during my time in New York.
خلال فترة عملي في نيويورك.
I negotiated for my country
فاوضت عن بلدي
the resolution in the Security Council
قرار مجلس الأمن
of the 12th of September 2001
في الثاني عشر من سبتمبر
condemning the attacks of the day before,
الذي يدين الهجمات التي حدثت في اليوم السابق،
which were, of course, deeply present to us
التي كانت حاضرة معنا بعمق
actually living in New York at the time.
نحن الذين كنا نعيش في نيويورك حينها.
So it was kind of the best of time, worst of times
إذن كانت أفضل الأوقات و أسوأها
kind of experience.
في تجربتي المهنية.
I lived the high-life.
عشت حياة مفعمة .
Although I worked very long hours,
رغم أنني كنت أعمل ساعات طويلة،
I lived in a penthouse in Union Square.
كنت أعيش في شقة صغيرة في يونيون سكوير.
I was a single British diplomat in New York City;
كنت ديبلوماسيا بريطانيا أعزبا في نيويورك؛
you can imagine what that might have meant.
يمكنم تخيل ماقد يعنيه هذا الأمر.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I had a good time.
كنت أقضي وقتا ممتعا.
But in 2002,
ولكن في 2002
when my tour came to an end,
أتت جولتي على نهايتها،
I decided I wasn't going to go back
قررت على أن لا أعود
to the job that was waiting for me in London.
إلى المهنة التي كانت تنتظرني في لندن.
I decided to take a sabbatical,
قررت أن آخذ عطلة مطولة
in fact, at the New School, Bruce.
في الواقع، في نيو سكوول ، في بروس
In some inchoate, inarticulate way
بشكل غير واضح جدا
I realized that there was something wrong
اكتشفت أن هناك خطبا ما
with my work, with me.
بعملي، أو حتى بي.
I was exhausted,
كنت منهكا،
and I was also disillusioned
وكنت خائب الأمل
in a way I couldn't quite put my finger on.
لدرجة يصعب تحديدها.
And I decided to take some time out from work.
لذا قررت أن أبتعد بعض الوقت عن العمل.
The Foreign Office was very generous.
كانت وزارة الخارجية كريمة جدا.
You could take these special unpaid leave, as they called them,
إذ يمكنك أخذ إجازات غير مدفوعة الأجر، كما يسمونها،
and yet remain part of the diplomatic service, but not actually do any work.
لكنك تبقى ضمن السلك الدبلوماسي ، دون أن تعمل بالضرورة.
It was nice.
كان أمرا جميلا.
And eventually, I decided
في نهاية المطاف، قررت
to take a secondment to join the U.N. in Kosovo,
أن ألتحق ببعثة الأمم المتحدثة العاملة في كوسوفو،
which was then under U.N. administration.
التي كانت حينها تحت الإدارة الأممية.
And two things happened in Kosovo,
حدث أمران عندما كنت في كوسوفو،
which kind of, again,
من قبيل، مرة أخرى ،
shows the randomness of life,
مايوحي بالصدف التي تقع في الحياة،
because these things turned out to be
لأن هذين الأمرين انتهيا إلى أن
two of the pivots of my life
أصبحا محوري حياتي
and helped to deliver me to the next stage.
و أعداني إلى المرحلة التالية من حياتي.
But they were random things.
كانا أمرين من محض الصدف.
One was that, in the summer of 2004,
أولهما ، كان في صيف عام 2004
the British government, somewhat reluctantly,
حينما قررت الحكومة البريطانية بشيء من التردد،
decided to have an official inquiry
بالقيام بتحقيق رسمي
into the use of intelligence on WMD
حول استخدام المعلومات الاستخباراتية عن اسلحة دمار شامل
in the run up to the Iraq War,
التي أدت إلى شن الحرب على العراق،
a very limited subject.
موضوع محدود جدا.
And I testified to that inquiry in secret.
لقد كنت شاهدا على هذا التحقيق بكل سرية.
I had been steeped in the intelligence on Iraq
وكنت قد تدخلت في اجهزة الاستخبارات في العراق
and its WMD,
وفي أسلحة دمارها الشامل،
and my testimony to the inquiry said three things:
وشهادتي في هذا التحقيق تمثلت في 3 أمور :
that the government exaggerated the intelligence,
أن الحكومة بالغت في موضوع الاستخبارات،
which was very clear in all the years I'd read it.
الأمر الذي كان واضحا جدا منذ أن بدأت أقرأ عنه منذ سنوات.
And indeed, our own internal assessment was very clear
وفي الواقع ، تقييمنا الداخلي كان واضحا جدا :
that Iraq's WMD
أن أسلحة الدمار الشامل في العراق،
did not pose a threat to its neighbors, let alone to us.
لم تكن تشكل خطرا حتى لدول الجوار، فما بالك بنا نحن.
Secondly, the government had ignored all available alternatives to war,
ثانيا : أن الحكومة تجاهلت عدة بدائل كانت متاحة عدى الحرب،
which in some ways
و التي لا زالت بطريقة أو بأخرى
was a more discreditable thing still.
أمرا مخزيا.
The third reason, I won't go into.
السبب الثالث : لن أخوض فيه.
But anyway, I gave that testimony,
لكن على أي حال ، قدمت شهادتي،
and that presented me with a crisis.
مما عرضني لبعض الأزمات.
What was I going to do?
ماذا كان عساي أن أفعل.
This testimony was deeply critical of my colleagues,
تضمنت شهادتي انتقادا عميقا لزملائي،
of my ministers, who had, in my view
وزرائي ، الذين، في نظري،
had perpetrated a war on a falsehood.
شنوا حربا بناءً على معلومات كاذبة.
And so I was in crisis.
وبالتالي وقعت في أزمة.
And this wasn't a pretty thing.
لم يكن أمرا جميلا إطلاقا.
I moaned about it, I hesitated,
لقد ترددت كثيرا...
I went on and on and on to my long-suffering wife,
وكنت في حوار دائم مع زوجتي التي استوعبت ترددي
and eventually I decided to resign from the British Foreign Service.
وفي النهاية استقلت من مهامي في وزارة الخارجية البريطانية.
I felt -- there's a scene in the Al Pacino movie "The Insider," which you may know,
أحسست هناك مقطع من فيلم ل آلپاتشينو بعنوان "The Insider" من الممكن أن تكونوا قد شاهدتموه،
where he goes back to CBS
عندما يعود إلى CBS
after they've let him down over the tobacco guy,
عندما تخلوا عنه لصالح تاجر التبغ،
and he goes, "You know, I just can't do this anymore. Something's broken."
حين قال" أتعلمون ، لا يمكنني أبدا القيام بهذا بعد الأن ، شيء ما تكسر و لا يمكن إصلاحه".
And it was like that for me. I love that movie.
كذلك كان الأمر بالنسبة لي، أحب هذا الفيلم.
I felt just something's broken.
أحسست أن شيئا ما قد انكسر.
I can't actually sit with my foreign minister
لا يمكنني في الواقع الجلوس مع وزير الخارجية
or my prime minister again with a smile on my face
أو رئيس الوزراء ، و الا بتسامة على وجهي.
and do what I used to do gladly for them.
والقيام بما كان يسعدني القيام به من أجلهم.
So took a running leap
كان الأمر بمثابة قفزة سريعة
and jumped over the edge of a cliff.
قفزة من على حافة الهاوية.
And it was a very, very uncomfortable, unpleasant feeling.
كان شعورا مزعجا للغاية.
And I started to fall.
و بدأت في السقوط.
And today, that fall hasn't stopped;
و إلى حد اليوم لم يتوقف ذلك السقوط ؛
I'm still falling.
لازلت أسقط.
But, in a way, I've got used to the sensation of it.
لكنني بطريقة ما، تعودت على هذا الشعور.
And in a way, I kind of like
وبشكل ما، أصبحت أحب
the sensation of it a lot better
هذا الشعوربشكل أكثر من و
than I like actually standing on top of the cliff,
أفضل من وقوفي على حافة الهاوية،
wondering what to do.
متسائلا عما يجب علي فعله.
A second thing happened in Kosovo,
أمر ثان وقع في كوسوفو،
which kind of -- I need a quick gulp of water, forgive me.
مما-- أحتاج إلى جرعة ماء المعذرة.
which kind of delivered the answer,
أعطاني الإجابة،
which I couldn't really answer,
الإجابة التي لم أستطع العثور عليها
which is, "What do I do with my life?"
عن السؤال : "ماذا أفعل بحياتي ؟"
I love diplomacy --
أحب الدبلوماسية.
I have no career --
ليست لدي مهنة.
I expected my entire life to be a diplomat, to be serving my country.
توقعت أن أمضي حياتي في العمل الدبلوماسي ، في خدمة بلدي.
I wanted to be an ambassador,
كنت أريد أن أصبح سفيرا،
and my mentors, my heroes,
مثل أساتذتي ، و أبطالي
people who got to the top of my profession,
و الناس الذين يشغلون مناصب عليا في مجالي،
and here I was throwing it all away.
والآن ها أنا ذا أضرب بهذا عرض الحائط.
A lot of my friends were still in it.
مازال العديد من أصدقائي يعملون هناك.
My pension was in it.
تقاعدي كان في تلك الوظيفة.
And I gave it up.
لكنني تخليت عنه.
And what was I going to do?
ماذا كان عساي أن أفعل؟
And that year, in Kosovo,
وفي ذلك العام، في كوسوفو،
this terrible, terrible thing happened, which I saw.
حدث ذلك الأمر الرهيب جدا الذي رأيت.
In March 2004, there were terrible riots
في مارس عام 2004 ، حدثت أعمال شغب فظيعة
all over the province -- as it then was -- of Kosovo.
في كل إقليم كوسوفو كما كان يسمى.
18 people were killed.
قتل 18 شخصا.
It was anarchy.
كانت فوضى عارمة.
And it's a very horrible thing to see anarchy,
وكان من المرعب رؤية كل هذه الفوضى،
to know that the police and the military --
ومعرفة أن الشرطة و الجيش --
there were lots of military troops there --
كانت هناك فرق عسكرية كثيرة هناك--
actually can't stop that rampaging mob
لا يمكنها وقف هذه الحشود الغاضبة
who's coming down the street.
التي نزلت إلى الشارع.
And the only way that rampaging mob coming down the street will stop
و الطريقة الوحيدة التي يمكنها إيقاف هذه الحشود الغاضبة التي نزلت إلى الشارع
is when they decide to stop
هي أن يقرروا هم أنفسهم أن يتوقفوا
and when they've had enough burning and killing.
و عندما يكتفون من القتل والحرق.
And that is not a very nice feeling to see, and I saw it.
لم يكن هذا أمرا جميلا يمكن رؤيته، لكنني رأيته.
And I went through it. I went through those mobs.
مررت بهذه التجربة ، مررت بتجربة رؤية الحشود الغاضبة.
And with my Albanian friends, we tried to stop it, but we failed.
وبمعية صديقي الألباني، حاولنا إيقاف الأمر ، لكننا فشلنا.
And that riot taught me something,
فكان أن علمتني أحداث الشغب هذه أمرا،
which isn't immediately obvious and it's kind of a complicated story.
لم يكن بديهيا لأول وهلة ، بل كان أشبه بقصة معقدة.
But one of the reasons that riot took place --
لكن أحد أسباب هذه الأحداث التي حصلت--
those riots, which went on for several days, took place --
و التي استمرت لعدة أيام--
was because the Kosovo people
كان أن شعب كوسوفو
were disenfranchised from their own future.
كانوا محرومين من مستقبلهم.
There were diplomatic negotiations about the future of Kosovo
كانت مفاوضات ديبلوماسية حول مستقبل كوسوفو
going on then,
تجري آنذاك،
and the Kosovo government, let alone the Kosovo people,
وكانت الحكومة الكوسوفية قد تخلت عن الكوسوفين
were not actually
لم يكونوا في الواقع
participating in those talks.
من المشاركين في هذه المفاوضات.
There was this whole fancy diplomatic system,
كانت هناك تلك المنظومة الدبلوماسية الوهمية،
this negotiation process about the future of Kosovo,
تلك المفاوضات الجارية حول مستقبل كوسوفو
and the Kosovars weren't part of it.
التي لم يكن الكوسوفيون جزءا منها.
And funnily enough, they were frustrated about that.
ومن الطريف أنهم كانوا يحسون بالإحباط إزاء هذا الأمر.
Those riots were part of the manifestation of that frustration.
أحداث الشغب تلك ،كانت تعبيرا عن ذلك الإحباط.
It wasn't the only reason,
لم يكن هذا هو السبب الوحيد،
and life is not simple, one reason narratives.
فالحياة ليست بسيطة، سبب واحد
It was a complicated thing,
كان أمرا معقدا،
and I'm not pretending it was more simple than it was.
و لا أدعي أنه كان أبسط مما كان عليه.
But that was one of the reasons.
لكن هذا كان أحد الأسباب.
And that kind of gave me the inspiration --
فكان هذا أن أعطاني نوعا من الإلهام--
or rather to be precise,
أو لأكون أكثر دقة،
it gave my wife the inspiration.
أعطى هذا الأمر إلهاما لزوجتي.
She said, "Why don't you advise the Kosovars?
فقالت : " لم لا تقدم نصائح للكوسوفيين؟"
Why don't you advise their government on their diplomacy?"
"لم لا تقدم نصائح للحكومة الكوسوفية فيما يتعلق بدبلوماسيتها؟"
And the Kosovars were not allowed a diplomatic service.
لم يكن مسموحا للكوسوفيين باتخاذ مصالح ديبلوماسية.
They were not allowed diplomats.
لم يكن لديهم ديبلوماسيون.
They were not allowed a foreign office
لم يكن مسموحا لهم باتخاذ وزارة للخارجية
to help them deal with this immensely complicated process,
لتمكنهم من التعامل مع هذا المسار بالغ التعقيد،
which became known as the Final Status Process of Kosovo.
و الذي أصبح يعرف بـ " الوضع النهائي لكوسوفو".
And so that was the idea.
وهكذا كانت الفكرة.
That was the origin of the thing that became Independent Diplomat,
من هنا جاءت فكرة "الديبلوماسي المستقل"،
the world's first diplomatic advisory group
أول مجموعة استشارية دبلوماسية في العالم
and a non-profit to boot.
غير ربحية، جاهزة للإنطلاق.
And it began when I flew back from London
وقد بدأت ، حينما عدت من لندن
after my time at the U.N. in Kosovo.
بعد قضاء مدة عملي مع الأمم المتحدة في كوسوفو.
I flew back and had dinner with the Kosovo prime minister and said to him,
عدت إلى كوسوفو، و تناولت العشاء مع رئيس وزراء كوسوفو ، و قلت له،
"Look, I'm proposing that I come and advise you on the diplomacy.
" انظر ، أقترح أن آتي و أقدم لك استشاراتي في المجال الدبلوماسي.
I know this stuff. It's what I do. Why don't I come and help you?"
لدي علم بهذه الأمور ، هذا ما أقوم به، لم لا آتي و أساعدكم"
And he raised his glass of raki to me and said,
فرفع كأسه لي ، ثم قال،
"Yes, Carne. Come."
" نعم يا كارن، تعال"
And I came to Kosovo
فجئت إلى كوسوفو
and advised the Kosovo government.
وقدمت استشاراتي الدبلوماسية للحكومة.
Independent Diplomat ended up advising three successive Kosovo prime ministers
انتهى الديبلوماسي المستقل ، إلى تقديم الاستشارات إلى 3 رؤساء وزراء متعاقبين في كوسوفو
and the multi-party negotiation team of Kosovo.
و لجنة المفاوضات متعددة الأطراف في كوسوفو.
And Kosovo became independent.
فأصبحت كوسوفو حرة.
Independent Diplomat is now established
"الديبلوماسي المستقل" مؤسسة حاضرة
in five diplomatic centers around the world,
في خمسة مراكز ديبلوماسية حول العالم،
and we're advising seven or eight
نقدم استشارات لسبع أو ثمن
different countries, or political groups,
دول أو مجموعات سياسية مختلفة،
depending on how you wish to define them --
أو كما يحلو لكم أن تسموهم--
and I'm not big on definitions.
لا أهتم كثيرا بالتعاريف.
We're advising the Northern Cypriots on how to reunify their island.
نقدم الآن استشاراتنا لقبرص الشمالية حول كيفية إعادة توحيد جزيرتهم.
We're advising the Burmese opposition,
ونحن نقدم الاستشارات للبومين
the government of Southern Sudan,
ولحكومة جنوب السودان
which -- you heard it here first --
والذي ان سمعتم
is going to be a new country within the next few years.
سوف تغدو بلداُ مستقلاً خلال بضع سنوات
We're advising the Polisario Front of the Western Sahara,
ونحن نقدم الاستشارات لجبهة البوليساريوا في الصحراء الغربية
who are fighting to get their country back
والتي تحارب لكي تستعيد ارضاً
from Moroccan occupation
تسيطر عليها الدولة المغربية
after 34 years of dispossession.
بعد 34 عاماً من حكمهم عليها
We're advising various island states in the climate change negotiations,
ونحن نقدم لعدة جزر نصائح فيما يخص التغيرات المناخية
which is suppose to culminate
والتي سوف يتم التحدث عنها في مؤتمر المناخ
in Copenhagen.
في كوبنهاجن
There's a bit of randomness here too
وهناك عشوائية هنا ايضاً ..
because, when I was beginning Independent Diplomat,
لانني عندما بدأت كدبلوماسي مستقل
I went to a party in the House of Lords,
ذهبت لحفل في منزل اللوردات
which is a ridiculous place,
وهو مكان سخيف
but I was holding my drink like this, and I bumped into
ولكن كنت احمل عصيري هكذا .. و أرتطمت
this guy who was standing behind me.
بالشخص الذي كان يقف خلفي
And we started talking, and he said --
ومن ثم بدأنا نتحدث .. وقال لي ..
I told him what I was doing,
اخبرته ماذا سوف افعل
and I told him rather grandly
واخبرته افكاري
I was going to establish Independent Diplomat in New York.
وانني سوف اقوم بتاسيس دبلوماسية مستقلة في نيويورك
At that time there was just me --
وسوف تتأسس مني بداية
and me and my wife were moving back to New York.
ومن زوجتي عندما نعود الى نيويورك
And he said, "Why don't you see my colleagues in New York?"
وقال لي " لماذا لا تتواصل مع اصدقائي في نيويورك ؟ "
And it turned out
وتبين لي
he worked for an innovation company called ?What If!,
انه يعمل ضمن مؤسسة ابداعية تدعى " ماذا لو ! "
which some of you have probably heard of.
والتي قد سمع بعض منكم بها على الاغلب
And one thing led to another,
وهذا قادني ..
and I ended up having a desk
الى الانتهاء على مكتب
in ?What If! in New York,
في مؤسسة " ماذا لو ! " في نيويورك
when I started Independent Diplomat.
عندما بدأت بالدبلوماسي المستقل
And watching ?What If!
وكنت أنظر الى عمل " ماذا لو ! "
develop new flavors of chewing gum for Wrigley
وهم يطورون نكهات جديدة لعلكة " ريلي "
or new flavors for Coke
ونكهات جديدة " للكولا "
actually helped me innovate
والتي ساعدتني
new strategies for the Kosovars
اكتشاف استراتيجيات حل جديدة للكوسوفين
and for the Saharawis of the Western Sahara.
وللصحراوين في الصحراء الغربية
And I began to realize that there are different ways of doing diplomacy --
وبدأت ادرك ان هناك عدة طرق للحلول الدبلوماسية
that diplomacy, like business,
الدبلوماسية مثل التجارة
is a business of solving problems,
لان التجارة ما هي الا حل للمشاكل
and yet the word innovation doesn't exist in diplomacy;
ورغم هذا مفهوم " الابداع " غير موجود في الدبلوماسية
it's all zero sum games and realpolitik
ان الدبلوماسية اليوم تعتمد على الكلام المنمق
and ancient institutions that have been there for generations
والمؤسسات القديمة والتي هي ذاتها منذ اجيال
and do things the same way they've always done things.
تقوم بنفس العمل بنفس الطريقة
And Independent Diplomat, today,
والدبلوماسي المستقل اليوم
tries to incorporate some of the things I learned at ?What If!.
يحاول ان يغير من هذه الاشياء من خلال الدروس التي تعملتها من " ماذا لو ! "
We all sit in one office and shout at each other across the office.
نحن نجلس في مكتب واحد .. ونرمي الكلمات فيما بيننا عبر المكتب
We all work on little laptops and try to move desks to change the way we think.
نحن جميعاً نعمل على اجهزة كمبيوتر محمولة صغيرة .. نغير كل هنية من طريقة جلوسنا
And we use naive experts
لكي نخرج افكاراً جديدة .. نستعين بخبراء ساذجين
who may know nothing about the countries we're dealing with,
احيانا لا يعرفون شيئاً عن الدولة التي نتعامل معها
but may know something about something else
ولكنهم يعلمون شيئاً ما ..
to try to inject new thinking
يمكننا ان ندخلها في طريقة تفكيرنا
into the problems
في حل المشاكل
that we try to address for our clients.
التي نقوم بها من اجل عملائنا
It's not easy, because our clients, by definition,
انها ليست وظيفة سهلة .. لان عملائنا ..
are having a difficult time, diplomatically.
يواجهون اوقات عصيبة دبلوماسياً
There are, I don't know,
وهناك عدة دروس ..
some lessons from all of this,
يمكن استخلاصها من كل هذا
personal and political --
سواء على الصعيد الشخصي او السياسي
and in a way, they're the same thing.
فهي بصورة ما متشابهة
The personal one
ان الصعيد الشخصي ..
is falling off a cliff
ربما يكون يتدلى من حافة جرف
is actually a good thing, and I recommend it.
وهو شيء جيد بالمناسبة .. وانا انصح به
And it's a good thing to do at least once in your life
انه شيء جيد يجب ان تقوم به في حياتك
just to tear everything up and jump.
ان تترك كل شيء خلفك وتقفز
The second thing is a bigger lesson about the world today.
والامر الثاني .. هو الدرس الاكبر فيما يخص العالم اليوم
Independent Diplomat is part of a trend
ان الدبلوماسية المستقلة هي جزء من المنحى
which is emerging and evident across the world,
والذي ينمو ويكبر عبر العالم
which is that the world is fragmenting.
ان العالم اليوم يتفتت ..
States mean less than they used to,
والسلطة تخف سيطرتها
and the power of the state is declining.
وعندما تخف سيطرة السلطة
That means the power of others things is rising.
فهناك شيء آخر تزداد سيطرته
Those other things are called non-state actors.
ان هذه الامور التي تدعى العوامل الغير-رسمية
They may be corporations,
والتي يمكن ان تكون مثل الشركات
they may be mafiosi, they may be nice NGOs,
او المنظمات الغير ربحية .. او شبكات المافيا
they may anything,
او اي منظمة اخرى ..
any number of things.
او اي تجمع ما
We are living in a more complicated and fragmented world.
نحن نعيش في عالم معقد جداً .. وهش جداً
If governments are less able
والحكومات تفقد تأثيرها
to affect the problems
فيما يخص حل المشكلات
that affect us in the world,
والتي تؤثر علينا في هذا العالم
then that means, who is left to deal with them,
وهذا يعني ان هناك طرفٌ ما يتوجب عليه التدخل للتعامل معها
who has to take greater responsibility to deal with them?
ولكن من يملك حس المسؤولية الكافي لكي يتعامل مع هذه المشكلات ؟
Us.
نحن !
If they can't do it, who's left to deal with it?
اذا لم يستطيعوا التعامل معها . من بقي لكي يتعامل معها - المشكلات - ؟
We have no choice but to embrace that reality.
لا خيار لدينا سوى تقبل هذا الواقع
What this means is
والذي يعنيه هذا
it's no longer good enough
انه لايمكننا ان نقوم اليوم
to say that international relations, or global affairs,
ان ما يحدث في العلاقات العالمية .. او الدبلوماسية
or chaos in Somalia,
او الفوضى في الصومال
or what's going on in Burma is none of your business,
او ما يجري في بورما .. لا يعنينا
and that you can leave it to governments to get on with.
او انه يتوجب ان نترك الامر للحكومة لكي تتعامل معه
I can connect any one of you
وانا اؤكد لكم انه يمكنني ان اربط اي واحد منكم
by six degrees of separation
بستة صلات
to the Al-Shabaab militia in Somalia.
لميلشيات الشباب العسكرية في الصومال
Ask me how later, particularly if you eat fish, interestingly enough,
اسئلوني لاحقاً عن هذا .. خاصة ان كنت تاكل السمك .. امر مثير للاهتمام .. !
but that connection is there.
ولكن الصلة هناك
We are all intimately connected.
نحن متصلين معهم بصورة مباشرة
And this isn't just Tom Friedman,
وهذا ليس فحسب قول توم فريدمان
it's actually provable in case after case after case.
انه امر مؤكد من خلال كل قضية تجري حولنا
What that means is, instead of asking your politicians to do things,
ولكن ما هذا يعني .. انه بدلا من ان تطلب من السياسين القيام بشيء ما حيال امر ما
you have to look to yourself to do things.
عليك ان تقوم انت بتلك الامور
And Independent Diplomat is a kind of example of this
والدبلوماسية المستقلة هي مثال عن هذا
in a sort of loose way.
انها طريقة من طرق الحل الفضفاضة
There aren't neat examples, but one example is this:
هناك عدة امثلة .. ولكن واحد منها هو
the way the world is changing
ان الطريقة التي يتغير بها العالم
is embodied in what's going on at the place I used to work --
يمكن ملاحظتها في المكان الذي كنت اعمل فيه
the U.N. Security Council.
انه مجلس الامن التابع للامم المتحدة
The U.N. was established in 1945.
الامم المتحدة اسست في عام 1945
Its charter is basically designed
وقد اسست في الاساس
to stop conflicts between states --
لوقف النزاعات بين الدول
interstate conflict.
وضمن الدول
Today, 80 percent of the agenda
واليوم 80% من اجندة
of the U.N. Security Council
مجلس الامن في الامم المتحدة
is about conflicts within states,
هو عبارة عن الصراعات داخل الدول
involving non-state parties --
والتي يقصد فيها الصراعات بين الاطراف الغير حكومية
guerillas, separatists,
الانفصالين .. والمتمردين
terrorists, if you want to call them that,
والارهابين .. او مهما كان المسمى لهم
people who are not normal governments, who are not normal states.
الاشخاص الذين لا يملكون تمثيلاً حكومياً
That is the state of the world today.
ان هذه هي حالة العالم اليوم
When I realized this,
وعندما ادركت هذا
and when I look back on my time at the Security Council
وعندما نظرت الى تاريخ مجلس الامن
and what happened with the Kosovars,
وما يحصل بين الكوسوفين
and I realize that often
ادركت
the people who were most directly affected
ان الناس الذين يتضررون
by what we were doing in the Security Council
بما نقوم به في مجلس الامن
weren't actually there, weren't actually invited
لم يكونوا حاضرين هناك .. لم يكونوا مدعون
to give their views to the Security Council,
لكي يعبروا عن وجهة نظرهم في مجلس الامن
I thought, this is wrong.
واعتقدت ان هذا خاطىء
Something's got to be done about this.
ويجب القيام بشيء حيال هذا
So I started off in a traditional mode.
وبدأت اتصرف بصورة تقليدية
Me and my colleagues at Independent Diplomat
حيث ذهبنا انا و زملائي في الدبلوماسي المستقل
went around the U.N. Security Council.
الى مجلس الامن
We went around 70 U.N. member states --
وتحدثنا الى 70 عضو من اعضاء الامم المتحدة
the Kazaks, the Ethiopians, the Israelis --
القرغيزين .. الاثيوبين .. الاسرائيلين
you name them, we went to see them --
كل ما يخطر على بالكم .. ذهبا لرؤيتهم
the secretary general, all of them,
والامين العام .. الجميع
and said, "This is all wrong.
وقلنا .. " هذا خاطىء ..
This is terrible that you don't consult these people who are actually affected.
لا يمكن ان تناقشوا امور اشخاص يتأثرون جداُ بنقاشكم وهم غير موجودين
You've got to institutionalize a system
لديكم نظام مؤسساتي
where you actually invite the Kosovars
حيث يمكنكم ان تدعو الكوسوفين
to come and tell you what they think.
لكي يخبروكم مالذي يفكرون به ..
This will allow you to tell me -- you can tell them what you think.
وهذا سوف يخولهم باخباركم مالذي يفكرون به ..
It'll be great. You can have an exchange.
وسوف يكون هذا امراً رائعا
You can actually incorporate these people's views into your decisions,
سوف تدخل وجهات نظرهم في قراراتكم التي سوف تتخذونها
which means your decisions will be more effective and durable."
وهذا يعني ان قراراتكم سوف تكون مؤثرة اكثر ومقنعة اكثر
Super-logical, you would think.
انه امرٌ منطقي .. الا تظنون ذلك
I mean, incredibly logical. So obvious, anybody could get it.
انه امرٌ واضح .. منطقي .. يمكن لاي احد القيام به
And of course, everybody got it. Everybody went, "Yes, of course, you're absolutely right.
وطبعا قال الجميع .. نعم حتما انت على حق
Come back to us
لنتحدث في هذا لاحقاً
in maybe six months."
خلال 6 اشهر
And of course, nothing happened -- nobody did anything.
وحتماً لم يحدث شيء من هذا القبيل .. لم يقم اي احد باي شيء
The Security Council does its business
مجلس الامن يقوم بعمله
in exactly the same way today
بنفس الطريقة حتى اليوم .
that it did X number of years ago,
كما كان يقوم بها منذ سنوات خلت
when I was there 10 years ago.
عندما كنت هناك من 10 سنوات
So we looked at that observation
لذا نظرنا الى التحليل ..
of basically failure
تحليل الفشل الاساسي
and thought, what can we do about it.
وفكرنا .. مالذي يمكننا القيام به حيال هذا
And I thought, I'm buggered
وقلت في نفسي .. انا متعب
if I'm going to spend the rest of my life
سوف اقضي كل حياتي
lobbying for these crummy governments
وانا احاور هذه الحكومات المتعنتة
to do what needs to be done.
كي تقوم بما يجب القيام به
So what we're going to do
يجب القيام بشيء آخر
is we're actually going to set up these meetings ourselves.
سوف نقوم باعداد هذه اللقاءات وحدنا ..
So now, Independent Diplomat
لذا اليوم.. في الدبلوماسي المستقل
is in the process of setting up meetings
نحن نعد لتلك اللقاءات
between the U.N. Security Council
بين مجلس الامن
and the parties to the disputes
وبين الاطراف المهمشة
that are on the agenda of the Security Council.
والتي يناقش مجلس الامن شؤونها
So we will be bringing
لذا سوف نجلب
Darfuri rebel groups,
اطرافاً متمردة من دارفور
the Northern Cypriots and the Southern Cypriots,
واطرافاُ من شمال وجنوب قبرص
rebels from Aceh,
ومتمردين من آتشيه
and awful long laundry list
وهناك الكثير من الاطراف والقائمة طويلة ..
of chaotic conflicts around the world.
بسبب كثرة النزاعات والفوضى حول العالم
And we will be trying to bring the parties to New York
وسوف نحاول ان نجلب كل تلك الاطراف الى نيويورك
to sit down in a quiet room
لكي يجلسوا في غرفة هادئة
in a private setting with no press
بدون صحفين بكل سرية
and actually explain what they want
ولكي يشرحوا مالذي يريدونه
to the members of the U. N. Security Council,
لاعضاء مجلس الامن التابع للامم المتحدة
and for the members of the U.N. Security Council
وان يشرح اعضاء مجلس الامن
to explain to them what they want.
تصوراتهم لهم
So there's actually a conversation,
وان يكون هناك حوار
which has never before happened.
وهو حوار لم يحدث من ذي قبل
And of course, describing all this,
وطبعاً .. وبعد كل هذا
any of you who know politics will think this is incredibly difficult,
اي شخص منكم يعي فيما يخص السياسية .. يعرف ان هذا شديد الصعوبة
and I entirely agree with you.
وانا اتفق معه
The chances of failure are very high,
ان فرص الفشل كبيرة جداً
but it certainly won't happen
ولكنها لن تحصل
if we don't try to make it happen.
ان لم نسمح لها بالحصول
And my politics has changed fundamentally
ان سياستي قد تغيرت بصورة جذرية
from when I was a diplomat to what I am today,
بين عندما ما كنت دبلوماسياً .. وبين اليوم
and I think that outputs is what matters, not process,
وانا اظن ان النتائج هي المهمة .. لا الاسلوب ولا العملية
not technology, frankly, so much either.
ولا التكنلوجيا .. ان يمكن قول ذلك
Preach technology
فالتكنولوجيا
to all the Twittering members of all the Iranian demonstrations
التي يستخدمها اعضاء تويتر في كل الافكار السياسية
who are now in political prison in Tehran,
الذين هم الان في السجون السياسية في طهران
where Ahmadinejad remains in power.
لان احمدي نجاد مازال في الحكم
Technology has not delivered political change in Iran.
لم تقدم تلك التكنولوجيا اي تقدم سياسي في ايران
You've got to look at the outputs, and you got to say to yourself,
لذا عليك ان تنظر الى النتائج .. عليك ان تقول لنفسك
"What can I do to produce that particular output?"
مالذي يمكنني القيام به لكي احصل على النتيجة هذه
That is the politics of the 21st century,
هذه هي سياسة القرن 21
and in a way, Independent Diplomat
وبصورة ما .. الدبلوماسي المستقل
embodies that fragmentation, that change,
يجسد هذا التجرؤ .. والتغير
that is happening to all of us.
الذي يحدث لنا جميعاً
That's my story. Thanks.
هذه هي قصتي .. شكراً